This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine, online at
computer.org/software.
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
I'm your host Gavin Henry, and today my
guest is Jens Gustedt.
Jens is a senior scientist at the French
National Institute of Computer Science
and Control. He's the former co-editor
of the ISO C standard and author of the
modern C book.
Jens, welcome to Software Engineering
Radio. Hello.
Is there anything I missed in your bio
that you'd like to add? I did keep it a
bit short cuz I know you've been doing
this a long time.
No, that's okay. That's okay. I have
much longer history for sure. I'll add
that.
That's more detailed show notes, don't
worry.
Okay, so
during the show we'll be talking about C
programming history,
legacy C, and then the last part of the
show talking about modern C.
However, I'd like to start with an
overview of where C came from and how
and why it became standardized.
So, what is C?
C is one of the
probably oldest but still
most used programming languages
uh
in history. So, it started in the '70s,
last century, long time ago,
and was much related to the creation of
what's nowadays the POSIX operating
system,
but
relatively fast became independent of
all of that.
So, the
essence at the time was
to have a programming language,
a higher-level programming language, to
abstract from machine specific things.
So, people could program in
relatively abstract way things that are
still relatively close to the machine.
So, this is where C
comes from at least originally.
And where was it actually created?
It was created
in the
Bell Labs, I think. So, this is all
related with at that time AT&T and Bell
Labs.
Where they had this research group
focusing on on operating systems and
these kind of languages. So, there were
precursory language was a precursory
language which is called B or was called
B, for example. And
people trying to
to
basic basically bootstrap what we
nowadays know as computer science in the
certain way. And would you class as a
simple language?
I think so.
At least it's
Yeah, it's probably the simplest
language of the major languages which
are still around.
So, it's much simpler than C++. It's
much simpler than Java
or Python or in a sense or it at least
it has much less features than all these
other languages.
And does it come with its own um
You mentioned Python. That comes with
its own interpreter. Is that
Does C come with an interpreter or
compiler or C is a C is a compiled
language.
So, it doesn't come with an interpreter.
It's compiled once and then executed
usually multiple times.
And where would you typically see it
used? You see it used in very different
kinds of
programs and environments.
One major
environment of where it's still used is
operating systems. So, many operating
systems today are still
written in C and the interfaces to the
to the system are
are formulated with
C functions and things like that. So,
most prominent prominently Linux, the
whole Linux system is written in C with
very, very little
assembly language underneath.
And many other systems are are like
that. So, this is one of the
really big usages of
C nowadays still is
everything which has to do with system
and low level. Yeah, I did a
show with Howard Chu on the lightning
memory map database, show 371 for
listeners that haven't heard of it.
And um
he picked C because it's the lowest
level language that you can do for our
speed and simplicity as well.
There is another related field
which is embedded programming
where you have these tiny little chips
that you have nowadays everywhere around
in your fridge or wherever. These tiny
little
chips which only have, I don't know,
bytes of memory or something like that
which just switch on your lamp, your
bulb or
things like that. So, there's
really a lot of a lot of these
processors now out there and basically
they are
programmed in C.
So you you you already touched that it's
very popular. So I guess if it's in
these types of devices and
operating systems
that's as popular as you can get.
Then there is an
a usage
which is a little bit orthogonal to that
which is
uh
high performance programming. So which
is
from a first point of view really quite
different from that.
But there C is used because it's
relatively simple, because it's
relatively good understood and because
the compilers nowadays are really good
in optimizing. So you're using C and
then
expressing your algorithm in a certain
way, your compiler can really well
understand what's
going on, what's that about, and how to
improve this with all these optimization
techniques that that are around
nowadays.
Doing vectorization, doing
all all kinds of constant propagation
and whatever they
they have invented.
So you've touched upon
compilers.
And that brings me on to what the
software ecosystem is around
C as a compiled language. I'm talking
about things like
uh the GNU e GCC compiler, Intel Clang.
Clang, yeah, the main ones.
Is there a mature, stable, easy-to-use
ecosystem around C? Uh
yes, I think so. So there are these
public domain
compilers that you mentioned. So GNU C
and uh Clang.
They're basically functional for every
processor,
CPU that is around that you can imagine.
So, this is really an advantage of C
also that it works it runs on all kinds
of processors everywhere. Then there are
a lot of lot of small compilers out
there for all these
tiny little chips which cost
maybe not a penny each or something like
that. There are a lot of compilers out
there that service these kind of things.
So, there is a lot of
compiler infrastructure there. Now, the
rest, let's say everything else what you
need to program C is an editor,
is a runtime system, and things like
that. So,
these are not There's not one system out
there to to to deal with your C or
something like that. Everybody has their
own editor, everybody has their own
loader, runtime, and whatever.
And um in relation to
standards, what is a standard
in relation to a programming language?
Sorry, I've used that word twice, but
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. For for at least for
me for me it's
important to have a standard for a
programming language because
a programming language is
is several things basically. It's For
one thing, it's a way to express your
idea of an algorithm and what you want
to do,
but it's also a way to talk to a machine
to the machines that you want to execute
your code. And the important thing here
is to be portable.
And if you want to be portable, you have
to say how will this program behave
independently on whichever CPU or
machine this will run.
And this is what the standard tells us.
The standard says, "If you do I plus
one, for example, then you will have the
the value which is incremented by one or
whatever things are written down in the
standard, how the arithmetic works, how
uh
basic functions work, how you interact
with the IO system, and a lot of things
like that. So, the standard tells us how
these things are supposed to work and
how a program is supposed to interact
with its environment. This has had been
done for C the first time in '89, so
this was the original
ANSI standard C from '89, which was then
take taken over by ISO, the
International Standards Organization.
And then there have been revisions of
that standard, the most important ones
in '99
and in 2011. And now we had a
let's call it bug fix release or
something, which didn't bring much new
features in
2018.
So, is the standard
you mentioned standard is there for the
processors
um
creators, manufacturers, but also the
programmer and the compilers?
The standard is there for everybody.
It's actually the contract that the
programmer has with the platform
providers or compiler providers. So, it
tells, "If you give me a program with
uh which is constructed in such and such
way, I as a compiler uh provider have to
deal it with it in that and that way and
do these and these things then with that
program. And the program has to behave
in a certain way. So, it's basically a
contract. And why was the standard
created for the C programming language?
What was the driving force behind it?
Uh the driving force behind it was that
when it was C was first developed, it
was developed for certain machine, which
was called
PDP-11 at the time.
And then it turned out that these
features this language had, everybody
wanted that. And so, they ported this
language to
their own processors, their own
operating systems, etc. And by doing so,
they extended the language, they had
some other ideas. So, everybody was
doing things a little bit their own way.
And if you And if you everybody does
their things their own way, at a certain
point
this is not portable anymore, because
you can't take a program which is was
written for the PDP-11 and take it to
another computer and so on. And so,
relatively quickly evolved
an idea of nailing these things down and
trying to fix things which were sought
to be essential to certain things, and
also leave some some slack to the
implementations to have possibilities
for extensions in certain areas, and
etc. But to nail them down to a certain
amount. Yeah, because there's certain
flags that you can have on the different
public compilers that you mentioned that
are only particular to that compiler, as
I understand it.
Yeah, there's certain flags. Is that
what you mean by extensions? There's
Yeah, certain flags, certain features
that compilers allow. And there is a lot
of things that are which in this C
jargon is called implementation defined
that depend on the implementation of the
of the compiler actually. For example,
how
how many bits an a normal integer has or
how floating point
arithmetic is performed and
some things which are in a certain range
to be defined by the implementation and
then the programmer can look up in the
document in the documentation or
or look into some some macro values and
things like that to know ah yeah when
I'm on this on this particular platform
this will behave that and that way. And
is the process the same as it originally
was or or has it changed just
to standardize a language? I guess you
mentioned that
there's little increments now
but I guess there's a lot of work in the
beginning. There is a lot of work in the
beginning. There's still a lot lot of
work.
Um
because the world is changing so so the
language also has to change and to
adapt. The process has I think not much
changed. I wasn't there in the beginning
so I can't tell you exactly how that was
done done in the beginning. In the
beginning there was this book by
Kernighan and Ritchie which basically
they described C which were the first
creators of the first versions of C and
I and they took that to into a standard
and they formulated and things like
that. Then you have these
now it's an ISO standard so then you
have these ISO procedures on how to
create standards and there's
a whole
uh
section of ISO for programming languages
so C is not the only one which is
normalized by ISO. There's also C++ and
Fortran and Cobol and I don't know what.
And there are certain procedures in
place, what you have to do and how how
you have to do that. So this is an
international standards organization
meaning that this is mainly driven by
the member states of ISO, which were
basically all countries in the world.
And uh
all progress
has to be agreed upon
by these national bodies that uh
that uh
participate in this uh particular
standardization of that programming
language. So And I think you've already
mentioned
why it's um
really important to use a standard-based
language, which It It is important to to
use a standard-based language to have uh
portability, basically. And to ensure
in particular forward portability, it's
uh so that when
in 10 years you will buy a computer and
you will run your program
of your company which
uh does certain things, this program is
still supposed to run on that machine.
Recompiled and things like that, but
then still to run there.
And um what enforces the standard when
you're writing code? Is it
at compile time that throws errors or
your tool set helps you or the
programmer? Yes,
this is basically in for C at least it
is usually basically the
the compiler or the the compiler does
the first first scan, let's say,
which uh is supposed for certain things
to tell you, "No, this part here is
wrong. This is not okay. I won't accept
that and so I won't compile your
program. Which is this is called in our
jargon a constraint violation. So you
have formulated constraints.
For example, you should not
add two
two integers which are too large so that
the sum will not
be be able to fit into into the machine
word of four four one integer. Things
like that are formulated and when the
compiler sees construct like that then
it will tell you no here you know you
have an error and you will have to
correct that. Where kind of programmer
get the standard from if they're
interested? Uh they can get it from ISO
directly
from from the International Standards
Organization which is re- relatively
exten- extensive to get. I don't know
something like
100 bucks perhaps or something like
that.
Yeah, I wondered why it's so much but
it's not.
but then you can also get it usually
through your national body which is
for example for France is AFNOR so the
French normalization institution or DIN
in Germany or
ANSI sits in
in the States I think and
usually then it's already a little bit
cheaper. And then you can look around
and look for
preliminary copies let's say of these
standards and you usually find
a copy
of these things
which you get for free somewhere. Yeah,
I think I bought the 2011 version for
40 bucks or something the draft one.
Um I'll put a link into the show notes
cuz there's a a nice page that tells you
where you can get them from on the
ISO 89c.org
or something.
I'll put that in. Um okay, I'm going to
move us along to the next section
which I've called legacy C.
So, now that we've covered what C is and
how and why it came to be standardized,
can we talk about legacy C?
So, what do you mean or what do I mean?
We'll go with what you mean cuz you know
a million times more than me. What is
legacy C versus modern C? And the
ultimate question is why did you write
the book modern C? You know, that's
where I'm heading to. Yeah. So, so as I
said,
C is now something like 50 years old.
And you can imagine that during the
course of these 50 years, people came up
with new ideas.
Uh machines have changed, compilers have
changed. And so,
the need is not exactly the same as it
was 50 years ago.
Then,
50 years ago, the
the software engineering
knowledge was not
yet as present as today. And
what I said about constraint violations,
formulation of strong requirements for
programs and things like that, they were
not
so much present in early C. So, an an
early C compiler would accept a lot of
construct
which nowadays would not be accepted and
which would
potentially have a lot of security
issues, performance issues, or things
like that. So,
the evolution of C has been to be a bit
more strict on constructs
and by that, catching errors much
earlier and especially at compile time
where where
old C or
legacy C would not catch that at all at
compile time and then perhaps crash at
runtime or something. So do we think
legacy C is a legacy compiler
or is there things in the C language?
Can you give me some examples of what a
legacy C program might look like or
functions from the standard library that
no longer exist, for example? Uh
there's only one function actually that
has been duplicated
which was
the get s function.
But there are
constructs which are now removed even
from the from the standard. One example
is the
interface for functions. Functions in
legacy C were
defined by what's now called the
Kernighan Ritchie
uh
header
function header style which was just
giving a list of the the parameter names
of the function.
And then after that
between this list and the function body
you had a declaration of the types of
these parameters.
But you did not have the type of the
parameters in the
uh declaration interface that you would
see from other parts of your program. So
basically you would know perhaps that
your function has five parameters but
you would not know that the first one is
an integer, the second one a double, or
whatever
you have there. Or you have to look that
up and you have to know that a
programmer has to know that but the
compiler wouldn't know it. Yeah, that
sounds more like um
an interpreted language, doesn't it? Um
it was not interpreted, it was compiled
to something wrong, if you did it wrong.
So,
uh
since C99, there are function
prototypes. So, if you use these
function prototypes, you have the type
and the name, and everything is checked
at compile time normally, and things
like that. Yeah, that's what I mean. I
mean, if you're using, for example, an
interpreted language, you need to go and
look up the API and check you're passing
in the right parameters. But, on the K&R
Yeah.
you couldn't do that before. The
compiler would just take whatever.
Yeah, the compiler would just take
whatever. It has some some standard how
to process these arguments, and how to
put them on the stack for the calling
function, etc. And, if the calling
function interprets them differently,
you your program would just do random
things and crash, and
and publish your credit card number,
or whatever. That would be the hacker
cracker terms.
Yeah.
That would be stack overflow, or heap
Yeah, for example, you could have stack
overflow, or any kind of misbehavior. Do
you think that's still as common as it
used to always be, if the compilers are
much better now? I guess that's a
smaller surface of attack, is it? The
the the the attack surface is certainly
smaller.
It's
uh C is still quite primitive. So, if
you if you do
what C calls cast, so so casting
away the type of a certain of a variable
to something else,
then you can still do a lot of harm.
Uh but, to to come back to
what's legacy C and what's modern C, so
this is for what I meant this
calling convention for functions was
something where where was, was a new
thing introduced in C99, which was
prototypes, and the old convention was
still kept until
last autumn. So, we just removed these
Kernighan Ritchie calling conventions
from C
just half a year ago or something.
So, that's from the standard, but that
might not be implemented in the
compilers.
That's from the standard point point of
view. From the compilers, they all had
to implement it still because it was
still in the standard, but usually the
compilers nowadays, if you if you are
trying to use the these interfaces,
would tell you something, "Do you really
mean that? I think you should perhaps
rewrite your function to be better or
something like that." But, uh so,
there's a whole line of progress
from this
legacy C to modern C with with more
interfaces that are more secure, and
also more efficient, and things like
that. So, this is why I found it
necessary at some point to write these
things up, and to emphasize on this fact
that there are more and
interfaces, more than things to do,
better things to do with C than the
legacy interfaces.
Because this traditionally C is really
long in deprecating things or even
phasing things out. So, things will work
a long time if you use old interfaces,
but and you're not not forced to to use
the new ones.
And this might be interfaces into the
operating system libraries or
the standard library. Interfaces into
the the operating system or means to
program. So, there
there are certain ways to program, for
example, doing
for for numerical algorithms, doing
matrices, passing matrices to the
functions.
There's a more modern way to do it where
you can basically propagate the bounds
of these matrices.
And but people don't use them because
they learned perhaps or their teachers
learned C 30, 40 years ago where these
things didn't exist. And so, they still
stuck into this more or less old world,
deprecated world of ancient C, ancient C
which
then never progresses. So, Maybe that's
the
title of the section, ancient C instead
of legacy C. Yeah.
That's pretty impressive there's only
one standard library function that's
gone in 50 years. Yeah, that's
That doesn't
doesn't need to be under emphasized,
does it? Yeah. Yeah, it is. It is.
If you if you look at other programming
languages, they are much more
pushy and deprecating things.
Oh, let's not talk about the JavaScript
ecosystem. You can
have a failing program within 2 months,
you know, it moves so quick. Yeah. Yeah.
So, this is uh yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. See See See people are really
conservative but
So, so they really hesitate to deprecate
things and
the idea, the driving idea is really
that uh
I want to be able to run my program that
I had 20 years ago and
perhaps still in the next 10 years or
something like that. Really
having
legacy in the sense of really having
code that is known to work.
Uh
that you can reuse that for for a lot of
years and uh
really uh keep up your investment
actually.
So it's
it's a good ecosystem and skill set
professionally and personally or even
hobbyist to invest in because
it's not going to change too much as
long as you keep on top of things. Yeah.
Yeah. And it's it's relatively easy to
keep on top on on on top of things. So
it's not not inventing something uh new
or every every year or something like
that. So And what tools, I mean, you
touch on some of them in your book, but
what tools are there to modernize your
ancient or legacy C? Just a modern
compiler or
Yeah, it's the the most important thing
is really a modern compiler to have a
modern compiler. And you have these
uh public domain compilers which are
cool really good nowadays. So GCC and
Clang really do a good job and have a
lot of uh
optimizations built in uh that work
quite well.
Uh the C libraries also are quite well.
So with C C is not only programming
language, it's also
the library C library which interfaces
to the which for to the operating
system.
And these are environments which are
really stable, which are really high
quality. And to that, in addition, you
have also vendor provided compilers and
vendor provided libraries for special
special architectures, for example, for
high performance computing. You have
uh these compilers from Intel, for
example, which are even better in
optimization for especially for Intel
chip sets and and things like that. So,
you really have
high-quality infrastructure for for
everything you you want to do. And
just to finish off this section, with
the compilers,
when would you decide to go for a
non-open-source one, to a vendor one?
Does it just depend on the sector you're
in or the type of program?
Prob- probably. It depends So, first of
all, you have to you have to be on an
off on an architecture where
where the public-domain
compilers work. So, they probably don't
work on every chip set.
So, if you are on some
particular embedded
processor or something like that, which
is new, maybe GCC or Clang don't work,
and you have to buy
the compiler which comes with the chip
set, which is provided by by the
by the chip manufacturer.
Um then, you have these compilers which
are really built for
for performance. So, so Intel is one of
the examples. So, you have Intel chips
in in many of these high-performance
computers nowadays,
which have thousands, hundreds of
thousands processors,
and every every cycle counts. And so,
you want to have something which really
is capable of using this architecture
as
as optimal as possible. And so, then you
would go for a vendor
vendor-based
compiler that
works with these things. That moves us
nicely onto the modern C
um or modern compiler section, we could
call it that.
Um, so just to um
summarize or mention again what is
modern C.
So, modern C for me is uh the C as the
standard defines it now.
And not 50 years ago or 40 years ago or
something like that.
And um what modern C
resources are out there for learning
more about that standard or how to
implement it, etc.
There's my book. Obviously.
Big tick for that one.
Uh You just need to stop there. That's
all you ever need in life.
Yeah.
Yeah, you you get quite far with it.
Um, otherwise, actually there's uh there
are a lot of books out there
about C and lot of uh platforms and
things like that. With a special
emphasis on modern C, not so much.
Much less.
And this was the main drive why I wrote
this.
Because I I saw that this
was uh lagging behind in some sense.
And then you, yeah, you have the
standard. I've I don't know. I I have a
certain view on the standard and I I
almost know it by heart. So, so probably
it's a wrong quest long wrong person to
ask. But for me, uh often it's uh just
the easiest way is to look into the
standard. And this then this construct I
want to know how this works and then I
look it up in the standard or how
this and this function
has to be called or
what are the special specialties of of
certain things and then I can look it
up. The
main part of the C standard has 500
pages. So, this is something
you can master in a lifetime
compared to other languages where it's
impossible, but uh
And um
given so much is in the cloud,
um we're in 2020, is modern C fully
compatible with continuous integration
and continuous deployment environments
to get your code into the cloud?
Uh
yes. I mean, you
This certainly depends on the on on on
the application. So, C by itself, it's
uh relatively raw. So, you
So, if you need
libraries to to to communicate between
your different um processes in your
cloud or have a database or whatever,
you need things on top of C. So, you
need you need the libraries and uh
access to things and access to a file
system and all that stuff.
And is there an ecosystem around this
like Python and parallel have their
different things. JavaScript has NPM.
Is there a go-to sort of C module
library place that you can look for
recommended and popular
things to build on? Fufufufuf. I
wouldn't know that too much. Uh Yeah,
you're
always waist-deep in the standard, so
you probably don't see that.
I'm waist-deep in the standard and
programming in really C itself, so
I'm doing doing things like that. So, I
do personally see
when you go on to um the various
different source code repository tools
online
that when you're doing your testing
file, so when you do a commit and it
runs your test week, it does have
off-the-shelf templates for C, so it is
obviously in the cloud like that.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, it's yeah, it's
probably. And all these uh platforms, so
so if you have Git or whatever, these
are
underneath they are themselves
implemented in C.
Yeah, again, the Linux kernel is
two of the most famous things written by
Linus Torvalds, aren't they?
Um
So, I think we've already covered and my
next question was
where do you see most of the work that
has gone into modernizing C?
I think we've covered that with the
standard.
Yeah. And the standard and the
compilers.
compilers. There's really a lot of work
going into the compilers, so this is
really the part
that is
really active and there's still a lot of
development of in in optimizing things
better and vectorization and
threading and whatever. And do you have
any insight into
the the teams and the workforce behind
the compilers and standards? Is it an
aging workforce or is there a new
is there always a new generation coming
in?
Uh I think the average age is half my
age, something like that.
That's interesting. That'd be in the
Well, for me that's in 20s.
For me For me that's a little bit more,
but
Yeah. No, there are a lot of young
people in there. That's good.
And I mean, this is a relatively
specialized thing, so if I see So, I'm
also
also scientists and and have PhD
students and have a group and things
like that.
That's why you kept mentioning vectors
and matrixes and stuff. That's
sort of in that field, isn't it?
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And
I see that the
PhD
students PhD students from our group
they because they really have this
relatively deep knowledge in in in in
compiler optimization and things like
that
that they easily get jobs in in these
companies
like Intel Google IBM
or whatever
because
this expertise is really sought and
and needed
for for for by these big
players to optimize their compilers.
We've done a few shows on compiler
design and how to create your own
language. I've completely forgot to put
them in the
in this
outline show outline but I'll put them
in the show notes after. I'd like to
talk a little bit about some of the
things I've seen in your book. So you
talk about
acquaintance
cognition and experience. Is that how
you say it?
Yeah yeah yeah Um
can you briefly explain what these are
and where these fit in a C programmer's
career?
The idea of the book was to organize the
book in levels. So having something like
a basic level at the beginning
and trying to get
people acquainted
with the basic things and how to write a
program and and keep things things
going.
And then there are certain other levels
on top which are more specialized more
complicated perhaps also and where you
really have to
be a bit more experienced as a
programmer to really appreciate them. So
you can read through them but if you
don't practice if you don't have
the the real problems at hand that you
for for which you need them. This
might not bring you so much
at least at that point. So, the idea
really is to have it
constructed
from the bottom to the top in in a
certain sense and have as far as I
remember, I think four levels, four
different levels of uh
experience or for for these things.
And the last level really is is is is
one where
probably people will see that in in
their whole career, every bite every
part of it at some some point. But, it's
probably
each of these points is perhaps only
interesting when you are really
confronted with that.
And would you get these different levels
from just working in in C or would you
recommend that someone
reads around the topic and
plays with other things to get ideas or
you know, how does that work? That's
just a normal career.
Usually in in programming still the
careers are that people learn things by
doing in in many parts. And
therefore, I hope that such a book can
can be a good thing to put beneath
somebody who's programming that
and giving the opportunity to reflect at
a certain point on
this and this point of view of of doing
things or uh
seeing how signals work or how threads
work in C and things like that. Having
something to relate to and look things
up perhaps after using them for a
certain time or being able to look
things up. So, probably such a thing
will not be read completely linear from
from
from front to the end,
but
coming back to it several times in
different parts of the career. What
modern things are there to make a C
programmer's life easier?
And that brings us on to what sort of
tools do you
see and personally recommend to make
your programming life more fun?
More fun,
Not that it's not fun, but
you know.
There's certain things. I already
mentioned these
different kinds of matrices and
and things like that, function
interfaces where you can put the bounds
of of your arrays and things into that.
There is for example something which
a lot of people don't use that could
could use them.
There are those things where people a
lot of people have to program threads
nowadays, so parallel programming in a
certain sense.
And
if you program threads, you have to
be careful that one thread doesn't erase
what the other has written, so you have
concurrency programs race races between
your threads.
And for
many many years the you basically only
tool to to protect you from from that
such things had been mutexes. So, you
would take a mutex in the beginning of a
critical section, do you think the thing
you want to do, and at the end relax the
mutex,
and then you're sure that during you
have that mutex, nobody else no other
thread can change the data on which
you're working.
This is
has a lot of performance issues and has
also a lot of
security issues because you have to
think of taking lock and think of
releasing lock at the end and
all these things.
Uh
since C11, we have a tool which is
called atomics where you can do
which are data types on which you can do
small little operations
just like that. So, you can have an
atomic which represents an integer and
you can add up one to that integer or
five or whatever you want to add and
you're guaranteed that all of this is
thread safe and uh you're guaranteed
that it uses the most efficient
implementation by the compiler
underneath. So, you have this feature
which is just a simple quali-
mostly a simple qualifier which you put
on to your integer. You say, "My integer
is to be atomic."
And then afterwards, you're guaranteed
that you can use it in a thread context
and you won't have problems with that.
So, this is an example where things are
really much simpler to use and more
efficient at the same time.
And which still is not used very much in
the community although it's there since
C11. No, I always understood it to be a
a mutex as well. Could you just give us
slight refresh on a thread in case
anyone hasn't come across it? I doubt
it, but Yeah, so threads are ex-
executions of the same program
in parallel. So, you can say in your
program, I want to do this and I want to
do that and do these two things at the
same time. Because you have multi-core
processor for example with several
cores. So, your machine can do several
things at the same time. So, you have to
have some way of telling it
I want these things done. I don't want
them to be done one after another. I
want them to be done in parallel. So,
would a thread correspond to a CPU, a
core?
Yeah, so a thread basically would
correspond to to a core. And these two
cores then can do their thing. And when
they're finished, they have to join
somewhere at the end and then
mix results or whatever whatever you're
doing. So, typical example would be
if And this is also something which is
in in the book. A typical example would
be if you have a game,
you would have one thread which is
responsible for the graphics
and drawing all these things. You would
have one thread which is
responsible for taking keystrokes, for
example, from the user or your joystick
or whatever you enter. And another
thread which would do the accounting of
how many points you have gained or
whatever. All these things are
basically independent.
You don't want to
for the graphics to wait that you that
you
put in a keystroke, for example. You
want these things to be to to run in
parallel. But they have to interact in
some way. So, they have to write
messages in a certain way or have to
tell each other, "Now there was a
keystroke, so perhaps you should
put a cross in that point here or
whatever you're doing in your game."
Okay, I'd like to move us into some
specific examples of what modern C looks
like
versus the things we see online in in
older books.
Is
is memory management classed as a legacy
construct? Do we still do this and what
does it look like now? The memory
management has not much changed yet. So,
basically, you still have the same
functions as you had 40 years ago, which
are malloc and free and some variants of
that to get dynamically get memory.
There is one aspect which is different
from legacy C is that you can
have
arbitrary large objects on your function
stack, so you can declare really big
vector on your stack.
But, this has pitfalls. So, so there is
this is
not so perhaps not such a good example.
Okay. Could Could you give me
two examples of what we shouldn't do
anymore that you see all the time?
What we shouldn't do anymore?
Yes. Basically, the most important
things that you should never do
is casts. And people do that all the
time. This is they take a pointer to
something to double and or to
Often they do it between float and
integers. They take a pointer to a
float,
which is
floating point value, so so so the bits
to to understand a floating point
value, you really would have to
understand the bits in a really
sophisticated fashion. And then they
cast this pointer to an integer and then
a manipulate this integer and then they
cast it back to float and hope that this
is still a valid
floating point, for example. Why do they
do that? Is Is it harder to do it
properly? Because they think that this
is this is more efficient. Because they
have learned in times 40 years ago or 30
years ago or their teachers had learned
that and have taught them
uh
that you have basically to be really
efficient to have you have have bit
manipulations yourself.
Which is not true anymore. In the
contrary, it's nowadays compilers are
much better of doing all these
optimizations and
then you can do them by hand and
particularly they do them well or they
will do them well even in 10 years when
your program runs on an architecture
where
what you never dreamt of
capacities chance. So So gone are the
days where you shouldn't trust Yeah, you
basically basically you should trust
your compiler. Yeah, yeah. I had another
question here which is what does modern
C make easy but I think you've touched
upon that with threads. That was a good
example. Thank you.
I love the takeaway section of your book
which is a
a brilliant cheat sheet because you can
go just go down the list and quickly
find things.
One I always like to see is item 7.6 for
but I've got the book.
Which is the on the
exit underscore success and exit failure
macros.
Where people normally put return one
or zero. Can you think of three of these
takeaways off the top of your head that
would surprise a C programmer that
learned C
10 20 years ago?
That they're looking down there and they
go, "Oh my god, I've seen that in all of
my code." And they need to fix it.
Sorry, I'm putting you on the spot.
Yeah, you're putting me on the spot.
No, I don't. No problem.
Sorry.
So
what's the hardest part of a C program
to write do you think?
The hardest part? Yeah, it's probably
the same with any program I would say.
Just a block
I'm not sure. I don't know.
I don't it's difficult it's difficult to
say. I mean, it's
in C usually it's relatively easy to
start things.
You you start an idea and then you get
easily mired into something and it gets
bigger and bigger, but this is this
probably the same for every programming
language. And then at some point finding
the the cutoff point and get things
shorter again and more concise and
better to understand and things like
that. So So that's probably the most
difficult part.
One of the difficult parts of C itself,
which is relatively specific, is as I
said, it's a permissive language.
So
it really only works well with
self-discipline.
So you can always C allows you to shoot
yourself in the foot. No problem. The
compiler has no problem with that. So
you really should follow
certain coding standards, certain rules
to what not to do. As I said, casts, for
example. If you disallow casts, your
code is 100%
more secure or something like that. You
should always initialize your variables.
There are
a lot of things like that where you can
have coding standards in your project,
in your company, for yourself, which
helps you to code well in C. If you
don't do that, if you if you just
write as it comes, write your code down
as it comes, and
just patch here and there, then you can
probably get very, very bad code, also.
Yeah, I think that's similar with a lot
of programs, but Yeah. C programs let
you do let you away with a lot. Is that
one of the main reasons for
Yeah, yeah, yeah. the infamous security
issues with C, or is that still so
common now that the compilers are
better?
Uh
there's still a lot of problems which
for for security in C because one of the
one of the
things that C does
in many parts is what they call
undefined behavior. So,
there are things which are not allowed
you're not allowed to do, but which are
difficult to track. And so, the compiler
might not tell you that this was not not
a good idea. Which is for example,
if you don't initialize your variables
and C still allows you not to initialize
your variables.
And you forget that and you pass for
example
pointer to a variable in a function
somewhere deep down. And then all of
sudden, somebody accesses this uh
variable and then the value there is
some complete garbage and then
everything goes haywire.
So, this is still something which can
occur. It still is a strictly typed
language though, isn't it?
It's a strictly typed language, yes. And
that's
strictly typed. So, your variables are
typed
and strictly typed.
But, you have casts. So, you can
try to cheat. You can still tell the
compiler, "No, no, this
I want to see this variable now as being
a such and such."
And then you also have the difficulty
that you have
everything which is allocated. So,
malloc only gives you a pointer to void.
So, there's no type there.
And you have to somehow put a type on
such a
such an object that you get by malloc.
Yeah, so that gives you some memory. And
it
gives you some
Yeah, it gives you some memory, but
yeah,
you're completely free to put something
in there with a whatever type you like.
And if there you get something wrong in
one part of your code, you interpret it
as a one type and another part you
interpret it as another type because you
you dig a little around with pointers to
this part or something, then you then
you may be in real trouble.
There's another part which is also quite
dangerous, which is bounce checking. So,
C has no built-in bounce checking. And
if you access vectors, you have somehow
to cope to know how large this vector or
matrix is.
And if you you're not careful and don't
use the modern tools that you have by
tracking these sizes of the vectors,
then you can
be in deep trouble because then you
access
elements beyond beyond the bounds.
What modern tools are you speaking about
there? The what what's called the
variable length arrays where you where
you put
the
the size also in
in the size which you pass over to a
function. And so, the called function
can know how large this
this array is. Does not only see a
pointer, but it also sees somehow the
length.
And you can
can then query this size and act upon
that size and be careful and think about
Okay.
I understand you're working on a in
quotes a common C C++ core specification
called N2494.
Yes. Can you tell us what that is and
why it is needed?
So, C++ is a sister language or cousin
or whatever how you want to call it that
deviated from C long time ago,
but still had connections to C. So, it's
a language which is moving much faster,
uh
much more innovation there, but also
much more
errors and things like that. So, they
had to withdraw things they had had to
the language and etc. So, in that sense,
C and C++ are somewhat complementary,
whereas C is really slowly moving
forward, and C is
moving very fast, but sometimes
two steps forward and three steps back
or something like that. And uh they
still have a lot of common syntax and a
lot of programmers actually which do
both.
And there are features in C++
which stabilized
years ago,
and which would be really good things to
have in C.
And on the other hand, for C++
in certain parts, it is
uh would be better to have more
stabilization
and
more this
uh
this compile-time type checked
uh aspect that C also has. So, there is
uh this
common intersection which would be
interesting, which could be interesting,
which is done by a lot of people in
certain sense. If you look on Stack
Overflow, people often mix up C and C++
and don't really know the difference and
things like that. So, there is really
some sort of intersection of a
community,
and the
I attempt I have started here is to
formalize that intersection a little bit
better,
and try to get to move the two
communities to agree on something like a
common this common intersection.
Excellent. That sounds really exciting.
Well, I'll make sure I get the links
into that
in the show. Yeah, which is kind of
project to have. So, I don't know if
this will succeed or how far we will get
with that.
It's not only about programming and
about specifying programs. This is also
a lot of social interaction.
Interaction. People who are
who are in their tribe in a certain
sense and which you have to move and to
convince that perhaps these other guys,
they also programmed since 30 or 40
years. They might have ideas which are
not bad and
and so you it will demand a lot of lot
of social skills also. Yeah, we I
remember listening to a show
on Software Engineering Radio before I
became a host where it was about C++ and
they were talking about the new
features in the spec similar to what
we've touched on.
And it did sound like there was a lot of
similar things. Okay, I'm going to start
to move to wrapping up the show. So,
obviously C programming has a bright
future,
but if there was one thing a software
engineer should remember from our show,
what would you like that to be?
I would want them to
look around
or to to not to not to get too much
stuck into their
things how they are
their habits are to do things, but to to
be open to
to look around and and how other people
do it and how modern ways to do things
that perhaps you have done since 30
years or something like that. So, really
this opening
aspect.
Are there some reference type of
projects or repositories that
you'd like people to look at or that you
go to to to look at some beautiful code
that's simple and done right? I I
particularly like the muscle C library
project, which I was at some point a
little bit involved.
Yeah, I think I've heard of that because
of you. Which which is
which was an independent C library
project created by someone was
say disappointed by the G lib C, which
is
the one which is basically
most of the time
used in Linux because this was too much
bloated and whatever a lot of technical
reasons, but what these guys have
implemented there is really a nice thing
of
really small functions, readable code,
really nicely done. I'm
for for people who at least who are
interested in
systems programming in C, this is really
good reference code to look into how
things can be done
with a good
coding
coding standards and and things like
that. It was
created for
embedded devices. So this is C library
which is really small also. If you if
you link it to your code, it's really
can just links the functions you need
and nothing else and and it's really
small. So this is really nice code space
to to look at. Would you reach for that
because you're in the embedded space
versus G lib C? I'm not really in the
embedded space. No, no, no, no. I mean
as a programmer, is that why you would
pick it or just because you want to
versus
G lib C? It's
it's at least as efficient, it's much
smaller and one of the main goals is to
implement the standard. So, glibc has a
lot of extensions, a lot of things here
and there. But,
to really use it, you have to know you
have to
to look into macros that are defined and
which version and whatever because it
changes also too much much. In musl, you
don't have any macro which tells you
that you are in musl because they
suppose that you are using the standard
and so you don't have to know
which implementation of the C library
you are. And um you spoke about having
variables
C strictly typed. Why does the compiler
let you get away with not
initializing that variable? Is that
something you can tell the compiler to
do?
Modern comp- Some of the compilers have
actually option to say, "Yeah,
initialize all variables." Some type of
default. It's a really relatively
new. I know of someone who just did that
for clang. I
if I remember correctly, and then looked
into the performance issues that could
come from that because the idea is that
they don't do that because they don't
want you to initialize the variable when
it will be changing right after anyhow
and things like that. So, so not wasting
any cycles. I see.
But, this is mainly obsolete nowadays
because they these compilers have such
good flow analysis that they are able to
detect when you never use a value, so
they don't assign that value anyhow, and
they only do the first real value that
is used afterwards and things like that.
So, the performance
decrease of something like that would be
perhaps 2% or something like that
measured.
Depends on your
Yeah, and if if you're in a memory
constrained environment, I suppose
having loads of initialized variables
would use up more memory.
No, it's more question of processing
time, I think. Depends, yeah,
depends on to which value do initialize
some variables, so
this can be a little bit more space
also, yeah. Oh, they would be compile
time, wouldn't they? So, it would be in
the binary.
Yeah. So, there are different aspects on
that. This is compile time, this is
space occupied, the front time. So,
there's but these are in the percentage
ranges and uh
compared to the security gain that you
get, I think for me that's a no-brainer
because uh
because there's so many security issues
because variables are not initialized
and
then have garbage values and
programs crash.
So, for me the security aspect would
come first. I first want to have a
semantically correct program and then I
want to think of how to optimize it, but
not first optimize and then see if it
does what I want to do. That's a perfect
explanation. Thank you.
Was there anything we missed that you'd
like to mention? No, I think we have
done a good tour, I guess. Yeah, we
could talk for hours
on this, but I've only got 65, 70
minutes. So, where can people find out
more? You've got a Twitter account.
How else can people reach out to you,
get in touch? I have a Twitter account,
I have a blog, which is not so active in
the last times, but still I sometimes
publish things on my blog. With
everything going on at the moment, we've
all been given more time, haven't we?
I suppose. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Exactly.
And
then there is a
webpage of for my book where you can
find things.
Yeah, I've got that in the show notes.
And where you also can
put in bug reports if you find a typo or
if you find uh I have some other
questions uh
you can also ask them there. And what
Sorry, this is a bit of a personal
question, but what is the the reasoning
behind
the free book on your website?
Um for me the reasoning is quite simple.
I'm a public servant. I'm paid by the
French state for doing the things I do.
And I don't see any reason to get a top
on
on my salary for the things I'm paid for
doing. Okay. Sorry, I just thought I'd
throw that out there. I was just
interested.
Well, that's a it's a good question.
I I have I'm also an editor of a
scientific journal and things like that.
So, I had
in some sense bad experiences with a lot
of
these scientific publishers, not the
book publishers, but but the
publishers of of scientific work where
we as scientists do basically the whole
work and write things up and write them
in LaTeX and whatever.
And then these guys publish these
things, don't give us a dime, and make a
lot of money off that.
So, you've cut that straight out by
making it free.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay, Egon. Thank you
for coming on the show. It's been a real
pleasure. Yeah, it was nice. This is
Gavin Henry for Software Engineering
Radio, and thank you for listening. Bye.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast including other episodes,
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE-Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.